Finding aid to the George Warren de Villafranca papers CA.MS.00389
Smith College Archives
George Warren de Villafranca papers
1922-1992
1951-1992
Smith College Archives
De Villafranca, George W., 1922 - 1977
CA.MS.00389
5.417 linear feet (8 containers)
George Warren de Villafranca was born in 1923 and became a Professor of Zoology at Smith College. The collection contains publications, research, grant applications, photographs, news clippings, and correspondence documenting his professional life.
Biographical / Historical
George Warren de Villafranca was born in 1923 in Meriden, Connecticut. He entered Yale University as a student of Zoology in 1942. His studies were interrupted by the onset of World War II and he became a radio and control tower operator for the USA Air Force in 1943. He eventually finished his undergraduate studies (1948) and went on to receive his Ph.D. from Yale University in Zoology in 1953.
In 1951, de Villafranca left the Marine Biology Laboratories in Woods Hole to take up a position at Smith College. At Smith, de Villafranca continued his research on contractile proteins in muscle. By the 1950s Burton Hall was considered an outdated facility for research and so de Villafranca and his students built a lab in one of the closets of Burton Hall. During summer, he took his lab to Wood Hole where he enjoyed state-of-the-art facilities and good sailing.
For his outstanding research and teaching, de Villafranca steadily rose through the academic ranks. He was promoted to Assistant Professor in 1954, Associate Professor in 1959, full Professor in 1963, and Gates Professor in 1974. In 1961, he was appointed Assistant to the President and was tasked with building a new science facility. The Clark Science Center opened in 1967.
Outside of his duties at Smith College, de Villafranca was incredibly active. He wrote nearly fifty articles on muscular contraction and won several grants for his research including a NIH grant from the National Institute of Arthritis and Metabolic Disease. He travelled to Germany as a visiting professor and to India as a consultant for the National Science Foundation. In 1971, he became the first scientist to deliver the prestigious Katherine Asher Engel lecture titled "The Driving Force: Muscle". De Villafranca was a fellow of the American Association for the Advancement of Science and a member of the American Society of Zoologists, the American Society of Biological Chemists, the Society of General Physiologists, Sigma Xi, the Biophysical Society, and the Marine Biological Laboratory Association. It is said that de Villafranca inspired so many of his students to enter the zoological field that many began to call meetings on the subject "de Villafranca Reunions".
De Villafranca passed away in 1977 after sustaining second heart attack. He was survived by his wife, Diana Fetter de Villafranca, Class of 1955, his children: Suzanne Stina Hans, Ruth Place de Villafranca and George de Villafranca Jr., and a former wife, Erica Pauli. His first wife, Suzanne Crane, died in 1960.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains materials related to the professional life of George Warren de Villafranca at Smith College. Materials contained within the collection include: photographs of de Villafranca's lab and his teaching, correspondence to other researchers, news clippings about his achievements, and a volume titled Remembrances written by colleagues and friends. Some of the collection is dedicated to de Villafranca's research and publications. These boxes include his published articles, his research notebooks, graphs and charts of various research projects, grant applications to fund his lab and his work as a consultant for the National Science Foundation in India.
Arrangement
The bulk of the collection contains research material. Correspondence and faculty materials are located in Box 1.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use with following restrictions on access: Box 8 is Restricted. Please see College Archives staff for assistance.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown.
Zoology -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Massachusetts -- Northampton.; correspondence; grants; photographs; research centers (buildings); research notes; De Villafranca, George W.; Marine Biological Laboratory (Woods Hole, Mass.); National Science Foundation (U.S.). Development in Science Education; Smith College -- Clark Science Center; Smith College--Department of Biological Sciences; Smith College -- Faculty -- Sources
- Associate Professor of Zoology, 1954 - 1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1951 - 1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence - Sherman College of Chiropractic, 1962 - 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Volume of Remembrances, 1977 - 1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Grants- AM 02647 Proposals, 1956 - 1957 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Grants- AM 02647 Renewal Application - Aug 1976, 1970 - 1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Grants- Biochemistry and Localization of Muscle Proteins, 1958 - 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Grants- Biochemistry and Localization of Muscle Proteins, 1971 - 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Grants- re-Embryonic Alterations in Pre-Dystrophic Muscle, 1965 - 1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Grants- General, 1952 - 1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Grants-India, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Grants-India, 1968 - 1969 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Grants-India- Correspondence, 1967 - 1970 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Grants-RG 4709 - C, 1957 - 1958 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Grants-RG 4709, 1956 - 1958 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Publications- General, 1959 - 1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Publications- General- Abstracts, 1960 - 1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- The A and I Band Lengths in Stretched or Contracted Horseshoe Crab Skeletal Muscle, 1960 - 1961 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- The Action of ATP on Natural Actomyosin, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Actomyosin Solubility and Skeletal muscle Emptying of Horseshoe Crab, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Adenosintriphosphatase activity in developing rat muscles, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Adenosintriphosphatase activity of Frog Myosin B., 1962 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Adenosintriphosphatase activity of myofibrils, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Adenosintriphosphatase Activity of Squid Mantle Muscles (Loligo Peatii), 1954 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Biology of Muscle Cells, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Contractive Proteins from Horseshoe Crab Muscle, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Contraction of the A Band, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- The Driving Force: Muscle, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Frog Myofibrillar Adenosintriphosphotase Activity, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Immunahistochemical Localization of Contractile Proteins in Limulus Striated Muscle, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Isometric Contraction in Glycerated Skeletal Muscle of Horseshoe Crab and Rabbit - I Relation of Tension to Muscle Fiber Dimensions, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Isometric Contraction in Glycerated Skeletal Muscle of Horseshoe Crab and Rabbit - II Calcium and Magnesium Requirements for Contraction 1970 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Isometric Contraction in Glycerated Skeletal Muscle of Horseshoe Crab and Rabbit - III Relaxation, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Limulus Striated Muscle, date of publication not identified (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Magnesium Activation of Natural Actomyosin ATPase from Horseshoe Crab, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Magnesium Control of the Calcium Myosin and Actomyosin ATPase of Limulus polyphemus, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Myofibrillar ATPase Activity and the Effect of Relaxing Substances, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Observations on the Anisotropic Band of Cross-Striated Muscle, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Paramyosin from Arthropod Cross - Striated Muscle, 1967 - 1973 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Paramyosin from Arthropod Cross - Striated Muscle - charts and graphs, 1971 - 1972 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Paramyosin from Arthropod Cross - Striated Muscle - Clam (V. mercenaria) paramyosin- mol. wt., 1971 - 1972 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Paramyosin from Arthropod Cross-Striated Muscle - Limulus Paramyosin - molecular weight data, 1970 - 1972 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Paramyosin from Arthropod Cross-Striated Muscle - photographs, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Phase Contrast Observations on the Anisotropic Band of Cross - Striated Muscle, 1955 - 1957 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- reviews, 1969 - 1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Sedimentation Behavior of Limulus Actomyosin, date of publication not identified (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Some Physico - Chemical Properties of Myosin B from the Horseshoe Crab, Limulus polyphemus, 1967 - 1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Some Properties of the myosin B ATPase Limulus, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Study on the Localization of Contractile Proteins in the Muscle of the Horseshoe Crab (Limulus polyphemus), 1958 - 1959 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- A Study on the Nature of the A Band of Cross - Striated Muscle, 1955 - 1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Superprecipitation of A Horseshoe Crab and Rabbit Myosin B, 1969 - 1970 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Ultrastructure of Striated Muscle from Limulus polyphemus, 1960 - 1961 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- charts and graphs, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- charts and graphs, date of publication not identified (Box 2, Folder 10)
- charts and graphs, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- charts and graphs, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- charts and graphs, date of publication not identified (Box 2, Folder 13)
- charts and graphs, date of publication not identified (Box 2, Folder 14)
- charts and graphs, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Limulus Paramyosin M and C.D and ORD., 1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Parocrystals, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Limulus Myosin, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Model E, date of publication not identified (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Rabbit Psoas - phase and electron photographs, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Glyc. Psaos electron microscope, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Limulus electron microscope, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Limulus electron microscope photographs, 2712 - 3165, date of publication not identified (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Limulus electron microscope photographs, 3166 - 3577, date of publication not identified (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Limulus electron microscope photographs, 3608 - 3723, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Limulus electron microscope photographs, 3724 - 3744, date of publication not identified (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Limulus electron microscope photographs, 4038 - 4315, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Limulus- extract of A Band, phase and electron microscope photographs, date of publication not identified (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Model E Log Book, 1962 - 1963 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Model E Log Book, 1963 - 1964 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Model E Log Book, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Model E Log Book, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Model E Log Book, 1965 - 1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Log Book for the Model E Analytical Ultracentrifuge, 1966 - 1967 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Log Book for the Model E Analytical Ultracentrifuge, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Log Book for the Model E Analytical Ultracentrifuge, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Ultracentrifuge Data, 722 - 900, 1967 - 1969 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Ultracentrifuge Data, 901 - 1083, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Ultracentrifuge Data, 1084 - 2049, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Ultracentrifuge Data, 2050 - 2157, 1970 - 1971 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Ultracentrifuge Data, 2158 - 2284, 1971 - 1972 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Ultracentrifuge Data, 2285 - 2400, 1972 - 1973 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Ultracentrifuge Data, 2401 - 2510, 1973 - 1975 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Ultracentrifuge Data, 2511 - 2662, 1975 - 1977 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Chromoscan Tracings - D.G. runs, 452 - 466, date of publication not identified (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Para, 1976 - 1977 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Vert. Physiol. - Zool au (1960) G.H. de Villafranca (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Electrophoresis, 196 - 305, 10/08/1974 - 07/17/1975 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Actomyosin Preps, 365 (cont'), 07/06/1977 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Orthoplan & E.M., 08/31/1971 - 08/02/1973 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Actomyosin Prep, 354 - 365, 12/16/1976 - 07/16/1977 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Actomyosin Prep Limulus, 342 - 352, 07/26/1976 - 12/15/1976 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Actomyosin Prep, 326 - 341, 01/21/1976 - 07/15/1976 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Actomyosin Prep, 316 - 325, 10/22/1975 - 01/20/1976 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Room 338 Limulus - Actin and Myosin - Prep, 274 - 299, 09/17/1973 - 12/20/1974 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Room 338 Limulus - Actin & Myosin Prep, 250 - 273, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Disc Gel, 468 -710, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Electrophoresis (slab) & D.G., 423 - 466, 1976 - 1977 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Disc Gel, 306 - 422, 07/18/1975 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- D.G., 17 - 195 - Electrophoresis, 03/27/1972 - 10/03/1974 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Rabbit Myosin - Burton 30, 05/01/1963 - 03/12/1975 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Miscellaneous Preps, 04/21/1970 - 07/17/1976 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Miscellaneous Preps, 07/21/1976 - 07/07/1977 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- T.N. & Tropo, 07/17/1972 - 03/07/1973 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Paramyosin Prep, 179, 03/29/1976 - 05/10/1977 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Paramyosin, 151 - 178, 02/28/1972 - 06/18/1974 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Paramyosin & Tropo Prep, 110 - 150, 02/28/1972 - 06/18/1974 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Limulus Actomyosin, 96 - 113, 09/01/1962 - 11/01/1965 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Limulus Actomyosin Preps, 48 - 83, 1961-1963 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Limulus Actomyosin Preps, 134 - 165, 11/01/1967 - 12/01/1969 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Limulus Actomyosin Preps, 166 - 179, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Limulus Actomyosin Preps, 225 - 250, 06/30/1971 - 06/19/1972 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- M. McCarthy Rm. 341 - Sr, 09/15/1971 - 01/20/1972 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Actomyosin Preps, 300 - 351, 01/20/1975 - 10/21/1971 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Limulus Actomyosin Preps, 179 - 196, 1968 - 1969 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Limulus Actomyosin Preps, 19 - 47, 07/01/1958 - 07/01/1961 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Limulus Actomyosin Preps, 1 - 18, 06/01/1957 - 03/01/1958 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Rabbit Myosin and Actomyosin Preps, 2-17, 03/01/1964 - 04/01/1968 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Myofibrils ATPase and Relaxation, 11/22/1965 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Limulus Myofibril ATPase Preps, 1 - 20, 07/01/1964 - 11/01/1964 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Paramyosin III Preps, 62 - 109, 05/18/1970 - 02/25/1972 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Limulus Paramyosin Preps, 24 - 61, 1968 - 1970 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Limulus Paramyosin Preps, 1 - 24, 1967 - 1968 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Limulus APK, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Pof Limulus Muscle, 1959 - 1960 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Frog Book VIIb, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Limulus Actomyosin IV Preps, 196 - 225, 02/17/1969 - 06/29/1971 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Frog Book VIIa AM & Para, 1961 - 1970 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Frog Myosin ATPase Book III My, 1957 - 1958 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Frog Myofibrils I, 1961 - 1963 (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Frog Book VI, 1960 - 1962 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Frog Book V, 1958 - 1960 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Frog Myosin IV, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Frog Myosin ATPase Book #2: De Villafranca & Hochgiaf My experiments, 1956 - 1957 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Woods Hole - Frog Myosin, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- a band of muscle - fine - structure, etc., 1958 - 1970 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Squid Muscle ATPase, Woods Hole, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Extraprotein of muscle EP #1, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Instructions for Muscle Research EP #2, 1955 - 1958 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Limulus Actomyosin ATPase #4, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Osboric Zool, 1951 - 1952 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Thesis III, 1950 - 1952 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Osboric Zool. Book, New Haven Thesis, 1949 - 1951 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Lorraine Gudas, Class of 1970: Honors Project, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Lorraine Gudas, Class of 1970, date of publication not identified (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Localization of Actint Myosin, Actomyosin, Paramyosin, & "Tropa" - Limulus Experiments 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Restricted (Box 8)